<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "/export/usr/local/forrest/main/webapp/resources/schema/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Voorstellen Masterproeven 2012-2013</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
      <p>Laatste wijziging: $Date: 2010-09-29 20:35:33 +0200 (Wed, 29 Sep 2010) $</p>
        <p>
          Dit is het overzicht van de masterproef voorstellen 2012-2013 van MA-ELO, terug te vinden in de onderstaande tabel.
        </p>

      <section>
      <title>Overzicht</title>

<table>
<caption>
Masterproefvoorstellen 2012-2013
</caption>

<tr>
 <th>code</th>
 <th>student(en)</th>

 <th>titel</th>
 <th>bedrijf</th>
 <th>promotors</th>
</tr>

<!-- voorstellen eindwerken -->

<!-- voorstel1 --> 
<tr>
 <td>voorstel 1</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Slimme Boiler: port naar embedded ARM platform (<link href="#boiler2arm">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>VITO ETE</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>

<tr>
 <td>voorstel 2</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Investigation of a conductive path at the Si interface in AlGaN/GaN HEMTs grown <br/>
     on Si substrate by Variable Magnetic field Hall (VMH) measurements (<link href="#conductivepath">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>EpiGaN</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>

<tr>
 <td>voorstel 3</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Investigation of the dynamic on-state resistance of high voltage AlGaN/GaN HEMT (<link href="#dynresistance">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>EpiGaN</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>


<tr>
 <td>voorstel 4</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Wi-Fi interference mitigation (<link href="#wifiinterference">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>Technicolor</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>

<tr>
 <td>voorstel 5</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Wi-Fi Radiated performance measurement strategy (<link href="#wifiradiated">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>Technicolor</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>

<tr>
 <td>voorstel 6</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Development of Wi-Fi analysis application on a PC (<link href="#wifianalysisapp">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>Technicolor</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>

<tr>
 <td>voorstel 7</td>
 <td></td>
 <td>Wi-Fi coverage improvement through high power TX (<link href="#wifihighpowertx">meer uitleg</link>)
 </td>
 <td>Technicolor</td>
 <td></td>
</tr>


<!-- einde tabel voorstellen eindwerken -->

</table>

    </section>

    
    <section>
      <title>Masterproefbeschrijvingen</title>

<!--
        <anchor id="hydrogen"/>
        <section>
          <title>Hydrogen generation from solar light – Experimental setup</title>

          <section>
            <title>Description</title>

            <p>
Hydrogen (H_2 ) is interesting as fuel for transportation and as storage of solar energy. There exist many methods to produce hydrogen. An environmental friendly way is the use of solar energy, which can be a source of hydrogen with quasi infinite lifetime.
</p>
<p>
The aim of this thesis is to develop a setup which demonstrates the generation of hydrogen by solar energy and the use of hydrogen for the production of electricity. For this aim a demonstration setup has to be developed, consisting of a solar panel, an electrolyzer, a water tank, hydrogen storage, a fuel cell, sensors, read out electronics and software. The solar panel converts solar light into electricity, which is consequently used by the electrolyzer to produce hydrogen (H_2 ) and oxygen (O_2 ) from water (H_2 O). The generated hydrogen needs to be stored. The fuel cell uses the stored hydrogen to generate electricity again. Sensors measure the power generated by the solar panel and the fuel cell, the hydrogen production rate, etc. This information is shown in an attractive way on a computer.
</p>
<p>
The thesis consists of developing the setup, selecting the different components and putting them together. Software has to be written to control the setup, read out the sensors and to give a nice overview of the setup.
</p>
<p>
      <img alt="figuur" src="eenfiguur.jpg"/>
</p>
<p>
Fig.1: (a) Een figuur
</p>


          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Contact person(s)</title>
            <p>Stefan.Degroote@imec.be or jan.genoe@iwt.khlim.be</p>
          </section>

        </section>

        
-->





        <anchor id="boiler2arm"/>
        <section>
          <title>Slimme Boiler: port naar embedded ARM platform</title>
          
          <p>
In het kader van het Linear Project is bij de afdeling EnergieTechnologie van VITO een Slimme Boiler
ontwikkeld. Deze Slimme Boiler stelt zijn flexibiliteit ter beschikking aan een Smart Grid.
Een eerste prototype van de Slimme Boiler is ontwikkeld rond een 8 bits embedded platform. Met
het oog op toekomstige eisen voor Smart Grid applicaties is een evaluatie van de toegevoegde
waarde van een ARM Linux platform interessant.
          </p>
          <p>
De opdracht voor de stage student bestaat uit:
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>
Evaluatie en selectie embedded hardware platform (ARM Linux gebaseerd)
            </li>
            <li>
porten van de bestaande applicatie naar het geselecteerde platform en optimaliseren waar
mogelijk
            </li>
            <li>
evaluatie van port in VITO Smart Grid test lab
            </li>
          </ul>
          <p>          
Kenmerken:
ARM, Embedded Linux, C, C++, Web services, Smart Grid Appliances
          </p>
          <p>
Profiel kandidaat
Master in Industriële Wetenschappen (1 of 2 studenten)
          </p>
          <p>
Stage begeleider:<br/>
Koen Vanthournout<br/>
Koen.Vanthournout@vito.be<br/>
014/33 59 16<br/>
VITO ETE<br/>
Boeretang 200, 2400 Mol<br/>
Geert Jacobs<br/>
Geert.Jacobs@vito.be<br/>
014/33 58 23
          </p>
        </section>





        
        
        

        <anchor id="conductivepath"/>
        <section>
          <title>Investigation of a conductive path at the Si interface in AlGaN/GaN HEMTs grown on Si substrate by Variable Magnetic field Hall (VMH) measurements</title>
          <p>
Supervisor: Jan Genoe, Stefan Degroote.
          </p>
          <p>
Company: EpiGaN.
          </p>
          <p>
Duration: 10 months (from August 2012 till May 2013).
          </p>

          <section>
            <title>Description of the topic</title>
            <p>
The objective of this master thesis is the investigation of a conductive path at the Si interface in AlGaN/GaN HEMTs grown on Si substrate by performing Variable Magnetic field Hall measurements.
            </p>
            <p>
During the epitaxial growth of III-nitride materials on top of the Si substrate, Ga atoms diffuse into the Si creating a conductive path at the interface between Si and the first grown nitride layer. This conductive layer is detrimental for both RF and high voltage applications because it causes low output power and low breakdown voltage, respectively. The technique used to investigate the conductive path is based on the Hall Effect. The parameters measured to characterize the conductive path are the carrier concentration, the sheet resistance and the mobility.  The aim of the thesis is first to build a setup for testing such parameters as a function of a variable magnetic field, by introducing a tuneable magnet in a existing Hall Setup. Then, by using that setup, the student will characterize the epilayer stacks grown at EpiGaN to investigate the conductive path in more detail. Specific sub-stacks will be prepared by the EpiGaN team in order to create a solid model to measure this conductive path. 
            </p>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>About the GaN-on-Si technology</title>
            <p>
In the past few years, Gallium Nitride (GaN) has attracted much attention due to several advantages over Silicon (Si) such as large band gap energy, high critical electric field, high electron mobility, high saturation drift velocity and melting point. Silicon Carbide (SiC) is a strong competitor but the SiC-based technology remains more expensive compared to both Si and GaN-based technologies. In 2009, GaN-on-Si technology started diffusing in several applications such as RF power amplifier. This has opened the door to the diffusion of this technology in high voltage power switching applications. The choice of Si as substrate enables the use of large size wafer diameter lowering the cost of the GaN technology. However, the growth of the III-nitride materials on top of Si is very challenging due to the large lattice and thermal mismatch between Si and the nitride materials which lead to several defects, dislocations and a severe wafer bowing.
            </p>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>About EpiGaN</title>
            <p>
EpiGaN was incorporated in 2010 by Marianne Germain, Stefan Degroote and Joff Derluyn, as a spin-off of imec. It focuses on providing world-leading III-nitride epitaxial material solutions for top performance devices. EpiGaN gives device manufacturers access to a unique, proven and powerful technology to be used in key market segments such as power supplies for consumables, hybrid electric vehicles, solar inverters, RF power for base stations, smart grid.... GaN-on-Si is the key technology enabler for clean energy generation and more efficient power conversion. Based on imec technology, EpiGaN focuses on providing world-leading III-nitride epitaxial material solutions for top performance devices.         
            </p>
          </section>
        </section>
      
      






        <anchor id="dynresistance"/>
        <section>
          <title>Investigation of the dynamic on-state resistance of high voltage AlGaN/GaN HEMT</title>
          <p>
Supervisor: Jan Genoe, Joff Derluyn
          </p>
          <p>
Company: EpiGaN
          </p>
          <p>
Duration: 10 months (from August 2012 till May 2013)
          </p>
          <section>
            <title>Description of the topic</title>
            <p>
The objective of this master thesis is the investigation of the dynamic on-state resistance in AlGaN/GaN HEMTs grown on Si substrate by design and implementation of characterisation circuit.
            </p>
            <p>
One problem with GaN High Electron Mobility Transistors (HEMT) is the so-called DC-to-RF dispersion, which limits the conductivity of the transistor when operating at high frequency (> 1MHz). The effect can be observed in transistor characteristics as an increase of the on-state resistance and decrease of the saturation currents. It is however difficult to accurately measure the effect because it requires very fast (~10 ns to 100 ns rise time) and high voltage (several 100 V) pulses which are heavily dependent on both the speed of the set-up’s switching devices and any parasitic inductances present. 
            </p>
            <p>
In this thesis we will investigate the design and construction of a circuit in a set-up that allows to accurately measure the dynamic Ron of GaN HEMT devices. Then, by using that setup, the student is required to characterize devices made using the epilayer stack grown at EpiGaN to investigate the impact of buffer traps on the dispersion. A possible path to expand this topic is to use the knowledge gained in the first design phase to design a real power conversion circuit around these devices.
            </p>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>About the GaN-on-Si technology</title>
            <p>
Power electronics is a very important topic in clean technologies, because more than 90% of all electricity passes through semiconductor switching devices. Any power saving at the level of the power conversion circuitry (improved conversion efficiency) has a huge impact on the amount of power saved... or wasted.
            </p>
            <p>
Nowadays, most power electronics are built in Si, e.g. IGBT for high power applications such as wind mills or traction or Si MOSFETs for lower power applications operating at higher frequencies. However, Si technologies are so advanced that they have reached their intrinsic theoretical limits, and new solutions are needed to further improve conversion efficiency. 
            </p>
            <p>
The next step lies in the use of wide band gap semiconductors such as GaN or SiC. The latter is relatively well established but remains very expensive. EpiGaN believes that GaN deposited on Si substrates is the only way to combine high performance with low cost. The choice of Si as substrate enables the use of large size wafer diameter lowering the cost of the GaN technology. However, the growth of the III-nitride materials on top of Si is very challenging due to the large lattice and thermal mismatch between Si and the nitride materials which lead to several defects, dislocations and a severe wafer bowing.
            </p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>About EpiGaN</title>
            <p>
EpiGaN was incorporated in 2010 by Marianne Germain, Stefan Degroote and Joff Derluyn, as a spin-off of imec. It focuses on providing world-leading III-nitride epitaxial material solutions for top performance devices. EpiGaN gives device manufacturers access to a unique, proven and powerful technology to be used in key market segments such as power supplies for consumables, hybrid electric vehicles, solar inverters, RF power for base stations, smart grid.... GaN-on-Si is the key technology enabler for clean energy generation and more efficient power conversion. Based on imec technology, EpiGaN focuses on providing world-leading III-nitride epitaxial material solutions for top performance devices. 
           </p>
           </section>
         </section>








         <anchor id="wifiinterference"/>
         <section>
           <title>Wi-Fi interference mitigation</title>
           <p>
Wireless are nowadays dominated by interference rather than attenuation from the environment. Technicolor is working on
mitigation methods (e.g. a better automatic channel selection method) but lacks the manpower to execute the required tests /
studies in order to get crucial information that can drive the interference handling.
           </p>
           <p>
More specific there an immediate need to start investigating effects such as:
           </p>
           <ul>
             <li>
How does a network react on in-band Wi-Fi or non-Wi-Fi interference (effects are typically throughput, Link Loss, PER increasing ... ?
             </li>
             <li>
How does a network react on out-of-band Wi-Fi or non-Wi-Fi interference?
               <ul>
                 <li>
                  For 2,4GHz this means the usage of overlapping channels
                 </li>
                 <li>
For 5GHz this means co-channel interference or 40MHz overlap interference
                 </li>
               </ul>
             </li>
           </ul>
           <p>
Many papers have been written on the matter, though none of them addresses the real issue at hand and are of no practical
value to companies such as Technicolor that is involved in actually building products
           </p>
           <p>
What can the outcome be?
           </p>
           <ul>
             <li>
A paper describing real world effects of interference
             </li>
             <li>
Guidelines on how interference can be:
               <ul>
                 <li>
Detected by SW/HW
                 </li>
                 <li>
Mitigated
                 </li>
               </ul>
             </li>
             <li>
Direct input for the Wi-Fi team on how to modify the current interference mitigation strategy.
             </li>
           </ul>

            <p>
               If you are interested in one of these topics for a thesis or an internship at Technicolor, or should you have
               your own proposal for a thesis or internship at Technicolor, please contact Lin Noeninckx via edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com.
            </p>

            <p>
            Technicolor Delivery Technologies Belgium<br/>
            Prins Boudewijnlaan 47<br/>
            2650 Edegem, Belgium<br/>
            edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com<br/>
            <link href="http://www.technicolor.com">www.technicolor.com</link>
            </p>
         </section>


         <anchor id="wifiradiated"/>
         <section>
           <title>Wi-Fi Radiated performance measurement strategy</title>
           <p>
Today the Wi-Fi team has been working a lot on the conducted aspect of the WTP (Wireless Test Program). The radiated part is
not so straightforward as there is huge variation on the test results due to the fact that parameters such as the environment and
actual test spot are not controllable (a DUT is never being placed in the exactly the same way twice, idem for the remote side
(client)).
           </p>
           <p>
The goal is not to perform exact measurements, but trend line analysis. This can be typically done either in the office for 5GHz
and in the football cantina (a few miles down the road of the Edegem office) for both 2,4 and 5GHz.
           </p>
           <p>
The target is to:
           </p>
           <ul>
             <li>
               Develop a measurement methodology based in "average RF" measurements e.g. via a rotation table.
             </li>
             <li>
Study path losses on defined test spots and try to predict "expected" throughput at the test spots, finally correlate
measurement with prediction
             </li>
           </ul>
<p>
If you are interested in one of these topics for a thesis or an internship at Technicolor, or should you have
your own proposal for a thesis or internship at Technicolor, please contact Lin Noeninckx via edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com.
</p>

<p>
Technicolor Delivery Technologies Belgium<br/>
Prins Boudewijnlaan 47<br/>
2650 Edegem, Belgium<br/>
edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com<br/>
<link href="http://www.technicolor.com">www.technicolor.com</link>
</p>

         </section>


         <anchor id="wifianalysisapp"/>
         <section>
           <title>Development of Wi-Fi analysis application on a PC</title>
           <p>
Wi-Fi analysis is today cumbersome for non Wi-Fi experts.
           </p>
           <ul>
             <li>
              There is a lack of understanding what the TCO / statistics parameters mean
             </li>
             <li>
              There only either CLI or atomic data modeling available without an easy front end to query the info
             </li>
           </ul>
           <p>
            Technicolor is working out ideas to get info out of the gateways and tries to indicate quality via remote applications. What is
            lacking and virtually impossible on remote devices is an "Expert debugging tool". The reason is simple, not all of the info can be
            made available in a data model hence remote applications cannot see the information.
           </p>
           <p>
            A software developer skilled in Wi-Fi (or DSP, telecom, ...) could develop a PC application (on Linux, Windows, MAC, android ...)
            which would essentially present a pseudo real time GUI that displays all analytical data that can be pulled out of the Wi-Fi driver.
            Depending how advanced the skills of the developer are, fully fledged trace dumps or log files can be built and saved, providing
            excellent debug information to Technicolorâs CTS personnel. Or a console could be foreseen to alter the Wi-Fi configuration and
            then the tool could show the impact of the changes via the GUI. The tool can also apply data analysis methods in order to predict
            link quality, interference ... . The possibilities are limitless. The tool could communicate via telnet or ssh with the gateway.
           </p>
            <p>
               If you are interested in one of these topics for a thesis or an internship at Technicolor, or should you have
               your own proposal for a thesis or internship at Technicolor, please contact Lin Noeninckx via edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com.
            </p>
         </section>


         <anchor id="wifihighpowertx"/>
         <section>
            <title>Wi-Fi coverage improvement through high power TX</title>
            <p>
Today, a lot of US companies seem to believe that Wi-Fi High TX power is "the" solution to coverage. Both in 2,4GHz and in 5GHz.
Technicolor did some measurements to contradict this but a thorough analysis (based on measurements and an analytical study)
could wipe such statements of the table once and for all hence Technicolor can sit around the table with its customers and
demonstrate the sense and sensibility of the high power WLAN story.
            </p>
            <p>
The end goal is to know where the boundaries of the optimization are and create some form of advice towards HW / SW /
product management as to what would be the ideal TX power setting (in combination with RX sensitivity, but this will become
obvious during the analysis) and demonstrate it practically if possible.
            </p>
            <p>
The analysis requires to benchmark our gateways versus known client devices (iphones, ipads, android tablets, laptops) in order
to see how the commodity of Wi-Fi devices is performing vs. our gateway and how we could optimize
           </p>
           <p>
            If you are interested in one of these topics for a thesis or an internship at Technicolor, or should you have
            your own proposal for a thesis or internship at Technicolor, please contact Lin Noeninckx via edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com.
           </p>
            
           <p>
            Technicolor Delivery Technologies Belgium<br/>
            Prins Boudewijnlaan 47<br/>
            2650 Edegem, Belgium<br/>
            edgmrecruitment@technicolor.com<br/>
            <link href="http://www.technicolor.com">www.technicolor.com</link>
           </p>
         </section>

      
      
          
       
      </section>
 
  </body>
</document>

